A Finding Aid to the Tomás Oliva Papers, circa 1969-1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Tomás Oliva papers
circa 1969-1996
Archives of American Art
Oliva, Tomás, 1930-1996
AAA.olivtoma
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
This small collection of papers of Cuban born sculptor and painter Tomás Oliva measure 0.2 linear feet and date from circa 1969-1996. Found among the papers are a chronology; life documents; exhibition catalogs, including one from the 1993 exhibition of three of the original Los Once Cuban artist's group forty years after their first exhibition in Havana; one letter from Cyndee Levy-Angulo; notes and poetry; a photograph of Oliva with José Antonio Díaz Peláez; photographs of sculpture, two sketchbooks; and loose sketches and doodles.
Scope and Contents
This small collection of papers of Cuban born sculptor and painter Tomás Oliva measure 0.2 linear feet and date from circa 1969-1996. Found among the papers are a chronology; life documents; exhibition catalogs, including one from the 1993 exhibition of three of the original Los Once Cuban artist's group forty years after their first exhibition in Havana; one letter from Cyndee Levy-Angulo; notes and poetry; a photograph of Oliva with José Antonio Díaz Peláez; photographs of sculpture, two sketchbooks; and loose sketches and doodles.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Tomás Oliva papers were donated to the Archives of American Art by Xiomara Almaguer-Levy in 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Biographical / Historical
Tomás Oliva (1930-1996) was a Cuban born sculptor, painter, and printmaker who worked in Havana up to the mid or late 1970s before relocating to Miami, Florida.
Born in 1930 in Havana, Cuba, Oliva graduated from the San Alejandro Academy in Havana in 1952 with a dual degree in painting and sculpture. He also attended the Royal School of Ceramic La Moncloa in Spain and Ecole du Mosaic de Ravene et Ceramique de Faienze in Paris France. He also studied art and film animation with Ivan Zeiler and stage design with Ladislav Vihodil while living in Havana.
Oliva was one of the founding members of the Cuban artists' group Los Once (The Eleven), active in Havana between 1953 and 1955. Los Once consisted of 11 painters and sculptors-Pancho Antigua, René Avila, José Ignacio Bermudez, Agustin Cárdenas, Hugo Consuegra, Viredo Espinosa, Guido Llinás, Fayad Jamís, Tomás Oliva, José Antonio Díaz Peláez, and Antonio Vidal.
In the mid to late 1970s, Oliva relocated to Miami, Florida and regularly exhibited there and across the United States, Canada, Brazil, Mexico, Spain, Europe, and Japan.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 1 series.
Missing Title
Series 1: Tomás Oliva Papers, circa 1969-1996 (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Painters -- Cuba -- Havana; Latino and Latin American artists; Sculptors -- Cuba -- Havana; Sculptors -- Florida -- Miami; Cuban American art; Artists -- Cuba; Expatriate artists -- Florida -- Miami; Cuban American artists; Painters -- Florida -- Miami; Sketchbooks; Photographs; Sketches; Díaz Peláez, José Antonio; Levy-Angulo, Cyndee
- Tomás Oliva Papers, circa 1969-1996; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Tomás Oliva's papers include an artist's chronology compiled by Juan Espinosa Almodóvar, certificates of marriage and naturalization, and a letter from Cyndee Levy-Angulo thanking Oliva for donating a pastel to raise funding for a neonatal intensive care unit at the University of Miami. Also found among the papers are photocopies of articles and reviews about Oliva, his artwork, and the Cuban artists' collective Los Once, including a copy of the 1993 exhibition Hugo Consuegra, Guido Llinás, and Tomás Oliva: A Reunion.
  There are ink, pen, and pencil sketches of sculpture and doodles and 2 sketchbooks; notes and poetry written in Spanish by Oliva; photographs of sculpture by Oliva and a snapshot of Oliva with the artist José Antonio Díaz Peláez.
  - Artist's Chronology, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 1986; 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letter from Cyndee Levy-Angulo, circa 1994-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notes and Poetry, circa 1969-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photocopies of Articles and Reviews, circa 1993-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photograph of Tomás Oliva with José Antonio Díaz Peláez, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Sculpture, circa 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbooks 1-2, circa 1969-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sketches, circa 1969-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)